<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en-US"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en-US" /><updated>2024-11-18T19:34:01+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Dr. DEB NARAYAN GARAIN</title><subtitle>Celestial Mechanics, Space Dynamics, Bio-Mechanics</subtitle><author><name>DN GARAIN</name></author><entry><title type="html">Did Calculus Exist in the Vedic and Post Vedic Periods?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/mathematics/history/2024/11/18/first.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Did Calculus Exist in the Vedic and Post Vedic Periods?" /><published>2024-11-18T00:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2024-11-18T00:00:00+05:30</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/mathematics/history/2024/11/18/first</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/mathematics/history/2024/11/18/first.html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction&quot;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When we think of calculus, most of us picture Western mathematicians like Newton or Leibniz, who are credited with its invention. But what if I told you that the roots of calculus could trace back to ancient India, specifically the Vedic and Post Vedic periods? This blog explores fascinating evidence from ancient Indian texts and mathematicians that suggests calculus wasn’t a modern invention—it might have been around for centuries before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-vedic-era-and-sulva-sutras&quot;&gt;The Vedic Era and Sulva Sutras&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vedic Hindus were more than just philosophers and priests—they were keen astronomers and mathematicians. The &lt;strong&gt;Sulva Sutras&lt;/strong&gt;, ancient texts meant for constructing altars, reveal a deep understanding of geometry. More surprisingly, they contain concepts resembling &lt;strong&gt;differentiation&lt;/strong&gt; (breaking something into smaller parts) and &lt;strong&gt;integration&lt;/strong&gt; (combining these parts back).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, when constructing complex geometric shapes, the Vedic scholars used principles that modern mathematicians would recognize as integral calculus. This knowledge wasn’t just theoretical—it was applied to rituals and astronomy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;post-vedic-contributions&quot;&gt;Post Vedic Contributions&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the Post Vedic period, and we meet mathematicians like &lt;strong&gt;Bhaskaracharya&lt;/strong&gt;, who took these ideas further. His works like &lt;em&gt;Siddhanta Shiromani&lt;/em&gt; include detailed calculations that align with the fundamentals of calculus. Bhaskaracharya discussed rates of change and sums of series—concepts central to differential and integral calculus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was centuries before Newton and Leibniz formalized these ideas in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-happened-to-the-knowledge&quot;&gt;What Happened to the Knowledge?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, the golden era of Indian mathematics didn’t last forever. Foreign invasions and colonialism disrupted scholarly traditions and destroyed institutions. Much of the knowledge was lost or scattered. By the time calculus was “rediscovered” in Europe, India’s contributions had been largely forgotten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;why-does-this-matter&quot;&gt;Why Does This Matter?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding the history of calculus isn’t just about giving credit where it’s due—it’s about appreciating the global nature of knowledge. India’s mathematical heritage reminds us that science and mathematics are collaborative efforts built over time, across cultures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;final-thoughts&quot;&gt;Final Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, did calculus exist in ancient India? While it might not have looked like the calculus we study today, the principles were definitely there. From the Sulva Sutras to Bhaskaracharya, ancient India played a significant role in shaping mathematical thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next time you solve a calculus problem, take a moment to reflect on its ancient origins—it’s a testament to the ingenuity of humanity across time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think? Share your thoughts or let me know if you’d like to dive deeper into this fascinating topic!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>DN GARAIN</name></author><category term="Vedic Mathematics" /><category term="Calculus" /><category term="Ancient Science" /><summary type="html">Introduction When we think of calculus, most of us picture Western mathematicians like Newton or Leibniz, who are credited with its invention. But what if I told you that the roots of calculus could trace back to ancient India, specifically the Vedic and Post Vedic periods? This blog explores fascinating evidence from ancient Indian texts and mathematicians that suggests calculus wasn’t a modern invention—it might have been around for centuries before.</summary></entry></feed>